okay you know I don't have an issue with
it but I but just knowing that it's
happening in the background because
first I just wanted a over with iniquity
have a kitchen and certainly above it
because there's some other things that
are brewing around us that I'm keen to
continue this conversation with you
especially with some of the work we are
doing in Oakland we and the climate
change work but also one of the
opportunities is looking it so the
council were quite interested in looking
it donut approach and a bit like what M
Salim's done and and absolutely in terms
of some of the conversations that I
started in London with cake is is the
opportunity to anchor it in an
indigenous way especially some of your
work acknowledging some of those
indigenous linking this dis donut that
has been going around just recently that
was coming coming out of New Zealand is
that that the work that you've been
doing with Cato is that somebody else
who someone started to pick up on on
looking at the donor Indian Caidic she
shed some of the conceptual things that
I've given here last year in London and
and and offsets connected with him but
their group and and it just so happens
that one of the Maori navigators was
also a close relation of mine through my
mum's tribal people and but we had admit
physically or until there that piece of
work brought us together and and and and
and just we sort of see it all where
ancestors must be guarding us because a
third person who's come into the circle
over the last couple of weeks
there's also another tribes cristinaw
hours from where my mother comes from so
the three of us on the same tribe
they're found different pathways to this
circular conversation in in so a lot of
the underpinning
thinking in values all aligned in
certainly that iteration that came out
would be what we call a Mari
interpretation of the donut because they
translated a lot of the existing terms
into Mari language but but and and where
I was sort of starting was a complete
different sort of view because it was
what what the victim Lee what the donut
picture represented was which is sort of
like I guess and for me I saw a seat I'm
feared of looking for how do you connect
the dots so to speak yeah I always look
at the spacing between the dots and
actually everything's really connected
so so what drew me into the doughnut was
actually the space in the sort of inner
circle for me represented the
earth-mother in the outer circle
represented the sky father and and and
and often you need to sort of appreciate
the the total view of that relationship
from the moon in so often that's where
you locate yourself in order to really
appreciate the fullness of those sort of
symbiotic relationship between the two
sequels and so and because in a what we
call a fuckup upper or genealogical
centered approach is they're the
children of the earth mother and if
asked why father they become guardians
of certain domains of nature including
humility and so the framing would be
what I'd call a fucker Papa centered or
a genealogical centered view as opposed
to a human sort of seem to be which was
sort of more about when you said you
know look genealogical the the way I
understand and I'm really so new to I
don't even want to talk about it but the
concept in or worldview is the worldview
of life as a planetary process and us
fully part of it so
it's really in North American native
indigenous and systematic way oh yes and
all my relatives yes Oh whole living
system interconnected by these
intergenerational symbiotic
relationships mmm and in those buying
beans are what we call fucka Papa and in
in the connections I'm not and this we a
genealogy doesn't fully reflect because
what's transmitted through those fucker
Papa relationships his knowledge is his
essence is venues are also trauma part
you know and and so and the other sort
of bindings of the whole universe so so
Tim's of that's why I like in terms of
your expressions and writings of your
own whole living system the whole pill
in it you know because what I hear we
new speak and then you're writing you
are talking be a fuckup upper in nature
you know and so so and that's why why
you're thinking in framing really
resonates with me in that sense because
you're you're bringing a real circular
view a regenerative view in and so in
indigenous will views are circular as
well in in the opportunity and this is
one of my leanings in London the
opportunity is to be able to create this
by Nakia love you and we're these two
circle systems can actually sit together
in the in it's actually the shared view
between the two binocular lenses there
creates a third space and and because
certainly in the experience for Maori in
New Zealand you know we we've had two
hundred years of imposition of square
systems through colonization
westernization and urbanization and
we're still dealing with long-held
impacts of that and in and in some ways
we struggle were in New Zealand
because the assumed view is the square
yeah and and and all it's done is it's
been like an eclipse it's just gotten in
between us in the circle view which is
nature which has always been sitting
there and and part of our work is I'm a
species with L disenfranchised displaced
Maori communities which is prevalent
across a lot of a number of indigenous
communities throughout the world where
there's been a significant busts
connection from your own circle systems
and so part of our own healing is the
return back to circle systems and
because the loss of language loss of
identity our own native tongue can come
across being jargon it doesn't mean
anything because of the US and so so
being able to utilize circular systems
thinking is a means to help navigate
heal and and and I think it's something
there the whole of humanity is seeking
in that way let me ask you something
there because because lately I'm to
think in like I had this wonderful
conversation with jewel glance Burke
where we talked about this notion of and
I would love to hear you a perspective
on this notion of Rhian digitization
whether you find that quite of putting
or whether in any way resonates with you
because I in my current thinking I'm I
sense more and more that one of the
original mistakes is to in any way
assume that land can belong to us rather
than that we are the land we were
expressions of the land we come come
from it and and
this is so fundamental and the same we
talked about this in London at meeting
at the Commonwealth for a bit is the
notion of time how that traps us that
the Western notion of time and so I'm
beginning like I love the way that
you're so willing to build that bridge
of that binocular overlapping circles of
and see and I'm also wondering how are
we all somehow colonial eyes in the mind
with certain patterns that will make it
really hard for us to even fully get
back to this dynamic flow participation
thinking because we don't even i
certainly the Western culture that
doesn't even realize how much just these
these thought forms already trap us in
kind of misperception yeah oh look I
think there and I'd use this term the
recirculation of humanity is really
critical so so how old people are elders
are really taking on this term RiRi
circle ization and cause little you know
for me language is really important I
think underneath that the reality is
about the reinterred in ization of
humanity and and literally in a sense
and this is sort of what our elders talk
about and so my day to day work I work
for a state our state ministry who are
ministry for children so we take
children and stake here if we break down
to a family family violence and Maori
children 80% of our population of stake
here and that and that's really a
reflection of the impact of square
systems impact on family this location
disconnection and so our elders sort of
talked about there in order to generate
well-being
for families in for children there
because we use this mirror for within
the Ministry of so we have this neither
flex bush in the way so the younger
shoot grows in the middle and then you
have the parent leaves and the
grandparent leave so crows sort of out
and so these are smiley saying about um
if you pluck out the young shoot of a
flex bush
we will ambough boot go and sing and and
and so the most important thing are
people people people so their flex
bushes as a metaphor for family and so
well there is a need to keep children
safe but our practice actually strips
the young shoot out of the family and
and and you know indigenous sense we
take it out of an indigenous plant and
going put it in an exotic plant in terms
of Kia and none can keep us the
appearance and all that sort thing what
what our elders have talked about is we
actually mean to uplift them transplant
by whole bush into a better garden in
order you know because it's about
conditions of poverty disconnection all
those sort of things so they talk about
the garden and so in their process of
realization or rien digitization we
literally need to replant ourselves back
into mother earth and allow those
systems the sort of healing ourselves as
well as part of their process in so
because we know in our fucker Papa in
our history there we are all indigenous
at one point and and and it's really the
biggest impact Maeby's been in the last
five hundred years or so you know from
Industrial Revolution chefs of you know
and it's in that time that we went from
we to me so from the value of the
clicked of in family to the end of the
jaw and property rights and all that
sort of stuff and actually it requires
us to return to the weak and and in some
ways covert nineteen has presented that
opportunity to start rethinking
resetting reimagining and so I think I
think the rien degeneration
or recycle ization as really critical we
did the conversation with wood job back
then Joe also pointed out that he told
the story of how if you think of the
colonizers that colonized North America
and most of them were indentured people
were people who in order to get the
money because they were starving in
Europe in order carried their money to
get into the new world which was being
stolen from other people and they had to
commit seven years or longer of their
life to work for the person who paid for
their passage so and and in similar ways
the feudal system of Europe was also a
system where the indigenous people of
Europe were actually somewhat colonial
eyes door in enslaved by by the holders
of the land so in some some extent is
this disconnection and this
colonialization of the mind has been
going on for all of us every em yeah and
it's this how do we
enable people to like I what you just
expressed for me in in kind of more
Western design language I call it we did
our job now is to redesign the human
presence on earth within the lifetime of
the people there that's transplanting
the bush that's planting us back into
into the living cycles of a dynamic
system that keeps evolving that is never
static this is how we're gonna do it and
this is the design your master plan
because now we figure that out it's
always a process of learning of a
community of how to be and fit in in
relationship with each other and with
the wider community of life in that
place and what I've realized is that so
much of that has actually to do with the
the governance structures that enable
and this is because we had a long
conversation about land rights and your
people who claiming back their rights
for that that territories and and the
whole process in new zealand around that
and it's all of us if we don't enable
through some kind of change of
governance system true subsidiarity
where people in place have the rights
and responsibilities to make the wise
decisions about what matters to them in
their place and what matters to that
place but in full responsibility of our
global family and the fogger Papa
lineage of the meme yeah the one thing
we might all disagree on a lot of things
but the one thing we need to agree on is
we are life and we have to create
conditions conducive to life in diverse
ways in each place but yes and so how do
how do we in this current system I mean
resilient is very hopeful at least from
the outside view like you've got got a
pretty inspired leader you've got not so
many people and you you seem to be a lot
lot further along on the healing between
the the first people and and the the who
people who arrived later and and
beginning to like even but I noticed
with a lot of em kind of English roots
New Zealanders that I know I'm always
impressed
how learning the language for example
has just become fully something there
that one one does but how do you see how
how do we heal systemically everywhere
how do we enable people to come back
into community and ask those questions
that your community is asking but anyway
you know I think I think certainly what
we're working towards an L space is
shifting the whole operating system and
and so so in the work we're doing those
so so I'm involved in an hour working on
a regenerative program which will
probably end up being a 50-year piece of
work around regeneration of a stream
catchment in in the southern part of our
city in Oakland which also happens to be
one of the socio-economic lis DePriest
places and so so in our logic that the
state of the stream reflects the state
of the people which is another good
state and and and so by so what what I'm
working with council what they've agreed
to is to allow the whole operating
system be anchored and indigenous
systems thinking because they see it oh
why do we have to step into their
binocular lens why can't we go straight
to one lens and let it be yours and and
that's pretty powerful because that that
means that we help set the conditions of
the garden and and so part of it is
using the garden analogy is you know
we're helping prepare the garden and we
won't be around for the harvest in that
scene so so what what so so what we're
focusing on was what would I fuck up up
I seem to approach me in in regenerating
those fucker proper connections to place
to nature in people and that we as the
indigenous community
because we see ourselves as part of
nature as part of the lane that we just
help provide the underpinning in order
for those generations to in grow beyond
it and and so um so one of those um I'm
so in the sense of New Zealand over time
it's a rien de Jennison or in digitizing
our systems here because in a sense
we've had an indigenous system Indian we
figure we had a Wisma stir system arrive
and I think over time and of and this is
about that contra being conscious about
how we navigate the space is there
there'll be come a time where we
actually get to to re-envision eyes the
system so so we take the elements of the
we semester system the elements of
indigenous system and then we actually
create this food space which will be end
up being a Kiwi system which is anchored
in the lane anchored in nature in people
in and and we're seeing glimmers of that
through the covert 19 response in
Auckland in New Zealand what's really
interesting is there now it looks like
we've not only flattened the curve but I
think it's our limit of 12th day in a
row where we've had no covered 19
positive teeth and so we're talking
about maybe the government decided next
Monday on going to level one which is
sort of going back to normal but just
closed borders and and so they weren't
dissipating that we would be there in 28
days just allow for those cycles of the
virus to reappear and so we're sort of
ahead well ahead of the models but
what's really interesting there's this
tension that it's come through and what
we've seen is this the strain between
the opportunity of what a postcode bird
19 New Zealand would look like in a
circular way versus the tensions of the
old system still holding on trying to
hold on and and say you're getting
sort of those typical focus on art about
the economic impacts and we got to get
back to work and recover and it's all
about growth and all those sort of
things and this is over so there's been
a failure if you like in some ways to
recognize the window of opportunity that
has been presented and and and I think
that's part of that power of observation
of sort of seeing the regeneration of
natural systems to sort of see the
resilience of our community in a way of
looking up to each other in and
responding I mean one of the great and
changes that that will stay no matter
how quickly they try to bounce back is
that so much that prior to this
situation was sort of trying to invite
people into don't you understand how it
all interconnects and how quickly things
controllably and how rapidly things can
change and people saying oh yeah that
sounds very or your systems theorist
your futurists you academic telling me
these things but now you can always
refer back to a embodied real experience
that has touched people on the planet
and I think that that will already help
us to at least speak about interbeing
and interconnectedness in a different
way and similarly in terms of the
response all this well that sounds too
grandiose and ideal idealistic of a
response you will never get everybody to
do this in that time change takes
generations now you can say well we did
undercover in six weeks more change than
we did for many years before that but
but I I just wanted to come back to this
in in this what I'm sitting with so much
is how you know that
Buckminster Fuller said this wonderful
thing M if you want to change the way
people think don't tell them what to
think give them a tool the use of which
will change the way they think yeah but
if you if you think that through then it
sort of invites the question
for example how to what extent is the
use of money in the way that it works
right now the tool that conditions how I
think about life and about relationships
and about everything that that whether
I'm still connected tribal indigenous
origin or where I am just an earth
earthling of being indigenous to this
planet
am i it still kind of influences
behavior in a way that if we don't shine
the light on it
even in this new synergy of bringing our
ancestral wisdom back into the human
family and using it to guide our
navigation into the future and what are
the key things that from from from from
your perspective we really need to be
careful with just taking like continuing
because the square system has
established it it works globally
everybody recognizes it for a few
generations we all grew up with these
circular structures others square
structures and therefore they they run
in the background without being
questioned understand what I'm trying to
get it totally because it's this unseen
force we use the tim-mah Tohono which is
hidden and so our ancestors for the wins
toughly mati is what we call our mutter
who knows a hidden force yo and you see
the impact or you might hear the impact
or pufferty but you never see taffy you
know it's that type of things so so part
of the old sort of little mentor is it's
sort of two things is you need to become
a way of the square in order to be able
to recognize the sickle and and it's
like your point earlier about not
telling people how to think but it's
just that to help reveal things and and
and and and and our young people and our
elders are the ones that really switch
onto that because I know see
is this purity of thought and clarity in
how they see complexity and and that's
and they and epic and they they become
almost my piece to what I call the
stuck-up upper centered logic hmm if it
makes sense to our elders and it makes
sense to our young people there we're on
the one you know because but it's and
sometimes you might have to frame it
slightly differently for each audience
but once they actually switch into the
thinking and that way they get it and
then it's like this revolution so we've
got your elders talking about
recirculation we've got our young people
talking about recirculation because and
and what we're talking about is that
there because what they're really
recognizing is using this lens of what's
queer thinking what circular thinking
and and and I and you know and what l.l
elders get because some of your elders
grew up in the time of literal apartheid
we're and some of our towns in New
Zealand there were signs we are only
whites only
no Marty allowed that type of thing and
so they that's part of their living
experience what what they're starting to
recognize is their beckon that they it
was the square and circle was as clear
and simple as Marty and non Marty what's
happened generations later is that
there's no ethnic distinction between
square and circle thinking and and and
one of the challenges is they're in this
sort of post-colonial
age is the tribes in the government we
can solve past issues and do these sort
of treaty settlements compensation
reparation type things is that the
structures they have to create and goes
back to your point earlier around
governance around leadership
decision-making pipe platforms as they
have to create a square system
governance system to manage those things
and then it shifts the whole way of
thinking and being from a circular
system to a square and and so we're
becoming really awesome about driving
our own square
within their own indigenous communities
and and so by being able to become aware
of the square and recognize the circle
because what what and and I think over
nineteen climate change it's almost like
certainly in our context for the last
200 years we've had this Eclipse occur
where what we thought where our circle
systems-thinking in knowledge has been
sort of replaced by these square systems
but what's really exciting is that
eclipses are starting to continue its
movement and we're starting to see the
circle reveal itself so so that's the
thing is the circle will always reveal
itself because the circle is nature it's
always there
there's just the squares districted us
and to the point it's become so
subconscious and so locked then we're
not aware of it it's like um sometimes
you drive to a place and you don't
remember actually the route or how you
got there but it's so engrained you
driving you know because these some
things we don't think we don't think
about driving we don't think you know
but we just get to you places so so
that's because and a lot of ways we've
lost the ability to observe to see no
signs for you later as you were just
describing this I had this this visual
image of in in the English language
there's this thing about I'm trying to
put a square peg into a round hole and
and and if you imagine the round hole in
the square peg the reason why it doesn't
fit in is that they're little corners
then that stand over the circle and they
need to be shaved off to put up again
and then if you did that
there's also bits of the circle that are
free that weren't in the square and it
is an it is a two things coming together
but I'm so so deeply interested in and I
think this is the exploration you you
know have with you people saying where's
the square thinking within us is to find
out what are the bits that stand over
the corner that will actually then
continue to impede our refitting into
re-envisioned ization like they're the
bio regionalist called it re inhabit
patient yeah we inhabiting the earth and
and I think all these notions are very
very very similar it's a coming home
it's a um it's but it's not from the
outsider coming home from the inside
native to the earth again and that said
the resonance of that sense of belonging
that seems of place that you feel in a
depth of your soul you know that that's
and and I think to like you sort of
recognize there in a lot of times where
your soul takes you and where you end up
being the place where you live in put
roots through as they're often it's an
odd memory that's drawing you home in
the first place in some ways you know
and and so I think I think one of those
key things being around there reinker in
that re su closing in that way is about
recalibrating our sense of time and and
we talked about bit so so these things
like systems we use so we so we we very
much hit a lunar stellar calendar that
we use up and time up until the
Gregorian calendar arrived in that teens
the lock everything fixed everything and
as you said nature's dynamic its
movement that's all about movement and
there you actually got to move with the
season as opposed to regardless of what
the calendar says you know and and so
using those sort of tools what we've
found is there especially with our work
with in urban communities is that we
what we call Mara Mitaka which is lmarti
Luna Stella calendar it's about it's
unique to place so there's no you know
you know we don't have like a universal
the lunar calendar for New Zealand
that's actually localized place-based
because that's those local ecosystems
those local cycles they're in even your
location in terms of we are New Zealand
we'll determine the the slight little
times and things movements in one Bay
next to the other Bay will have its own
calibration you know so so being able to
attune ourselves recalibrate our
relationship to time and I think that's
one thing that covered nineteen forced
it forced actually slowing down of
chronological time mmm and you actually
hit the be in the moment and you had to
be in the state of where to fully
receive have that time or family all
those things because I'm all those other
drivers around chronological time no
longer existed or met it and and so
those families that were able to
recalibrate their sense of time the
sense of relationships do place actually
did really well through the lock down
again so so it's those sort of things
about and I think this is where some of
your indigenous knowledge tools if you
like can next be help because those are
the things they almost help us connect
into the space between the circle in
what the square P glue a end and and I
think because it is about and we sort of
talk about their recalibration processes
we use the tomb location location
location
so tell you locate yourself within a
certain worldview if you like it's also
how you anchor yourself to place and the
third shift is how you locate yourself
in a relationship with time and and and
as sense of I think Greek used the cross
you know that Chronos and Kairos is here
so in their kurios time it's it's where
a moment can last for Yuma and in that
time you actually get to commune with
your ancestors and your descendants to
come you know because it's a time-space
type continuum and and so you know and
this is where we've sort of seen the
deeper sort of contrast the depth of the
colors of
you know you can look at green but these
dips of green and you know because your
your viewers shuffling and so we've done
it with a lot of families and so we've
developed um like we have a Mari
language version of ale calendar but we
also have a non mari vision because some
of the families we deal with might be
Maori but don't have language don't you
know so so this is their first tip of
just recalibrating themselves back to
those fucker proper systems this is
fascinating for me because I I a couple
of weeks ago I talked to a man called
Martin from Hildebrand who lives in
Colombia and it's been 40 years helping
[Music]
tribes living in the Amazonian
rainforest to gain the rights over their
territory and support them in their
ability to continue that their
traditional ways and it's it's one of
the few places in Amazonia where where
that means we're talking about thirty
five million hectares of rainforest
having been turned over to two thirty
thirty-five tribal nations and they was
saying to him that in this storytelling
the traditions the the dances the the
songs and everything communicated the
circular patterns that you say the
location-based do not Hollander that is
different from one way to another and
it's it's may be expressed in a language
that says you can't go from from that
time to that time you can't go to this
area because the spirits are there and
they're doing and there's a story around
the two spirits doing what whatever but
what it's also and this is where they
overlapping of the two lens system but
it's actually also doing indirectly is
that in that area of the forest there
might be some species in reproduction
around that time and and if you want to
replenish that so so there's there are
these layers that are
wrapped him in indifferent storytelling
in different mythology and different
frameworks that actually have enabled
the oral tradition and the communication
through much longer time than our
Western II yes realization has lasted
and in how to in this conversation with
Martine he was actually saying how death
now come to him saying we have this
problem that our young after day in if
we do a three day ceremony after day and
a half they say how much longer is gonna
go on and can go and do this that and
the other
can I get my mobile phone again and and
in what what they in a slightly strange
way they turned into that skid and said
okay you help us communicate this
knowledge through your little video on
the mobile phone and through your
friends to and and if you want to create
a YouTube channel because that's what
everybody does know and of course that
it's I find it a bit awkward because
again I'm wondering how much does the
use of that tool change the what is
contained in in that long lineage of
tradition but but M how do we reap
discover in this globalized attention
world where particularly if we don't
reach analyze economic systems as well
as systems of governance and it will
always pull our attention what's going
on out in the global we have so much
learning to do to get back to that kind
of level of awareness of our
participation in the ecosystem that we
are at URI tell the stories of knowing
like here on my orchids it's the
diversity that Kay created the security
of having 150 species of almonds so
because they all flower slightly
differently and some depending on what
the climate does at least you have some
almonds and any like
do you find that you've found effective
ways of because you said if you if you
elders talk about it and you young
people talk about did you know and how
do you enable that so I think I think
what I think one of those challenges is
how technology is an enabler but every
generation history has had to deal with
technology in some form you know and I
think about my sisters we in the potato
James Cook bought the potato to New
Zealand and and that was one of the most
transformational pieces of technology
that there as an outcome it enabled us
to have two potato crops a year it led
to the creation of more settled villages
as opposed to moving across the our
resource spaces on this cycle you know
from the sea to inland you know he wears
so so I think each generation has had to
contend with technology in some form or
another and when you think about
indigenous people I mean I just thinking
that this and my mum Tunes alias she and
just symptoms of what she's witnessed
there near 80 years because you know
when she was growing up on the bomb you
know they walk eight miles on the middle
runner on a gravel road for them rode a
horse you know and and in her lifetime
she got to see someone go to the moon a
microwave get a meeting you know all
that sort of thing
and and and and and in just in terms of
you know we've only had to experience
this sort of system squeeze system for
two hundred years so we're relatively
young and it seems other indigenous
peoples a bit longer you know when you
think about North America South American
places like there and and and but we've
hit the consistency of the British in
that time too so so from a Commonwealth
perspective it's been helpful in
communicating with and the other
indigenous and communities because we've
got similar English symbology language
although
sort of things so we can go to other
parts of the Commonwealth in still feel
at home in that seats because of the
symbols of British Empire you know so I
think the key is the most important
thing is that intergenerational transfer
of values because that that's what has
maintained our resilience for a thousand
years within New Zealand
and on the back of fifty thousand years
and the Pacific could be like so so
that's the critical part and and I think
what we've seen is a displacement of
values and and and so so one of those
interesting points so one of those
things at the moment early on dealing
with climate change is around going m
Academy what I find really interesting
is it just focused on on the future it
doesn't really acknowledge the past
there's a way of helping anchor values
inca for cut you know because of that
sense of connectedness over time and so
I think that so al conversation of the
young people is and they fall into the
whole thing like oh can we do it
can we do a madam attacker app and and
and what we sort of talk about is sort
of two things that phone but the the
digital phone is really good like a
diary for recording observing you know
recording your observation camera film
all that sort of stuff
talking diary what I can't do is you
actually connect with NATO so it can
help support that and and and I see
because it's nothing like going they
actually step outside and have a look at
what the moon is doing the apps not
going to really tell you you know so so
it's about and I think the critical
thing is goes back to the storytelling
so the storytelling is really the form
that the code is the libitum and it's
the code within the stories which is the
important stuff so like your point you
made around the elders saying oh look we
don't go to that part
the bush at that certain time because of
the spirits now underneath it they would
have been like we've seen some other
reason why they the story just creates
that you know because it's about
stopping people going over the year to
certain time of the year so so and this
is part of the language so and the way
the Western square system have said are
those are just myths and legions there's
actually the other holders of the code
and and and and so um so the opportunity
is how can the next couple of
generations in their context be able to
encode those stories with the code
because it's about the code and if they
able to share the code for YouTube or
whatever form in order to help connect
the values in that's the most important
thing because often we get caught up at
that super at the surface level of this
technology it's actually if we put that
tick technology within a circle system
then that's all good it's sort of their
methodology and method mm-hmm so using
screen methods and a circle methodology
but it's all good because of the context
there it's it's um and how you're using
it and as opposed to square technology
in a square system that's that that's
the risk and that's their shift
displacement or values so it's not so
much the tick itself it's a system that
detects it's um and and that's how we
sort of explain what the operating
system like what the whole operating
system whole systems are is that you can
have different models of practice that
are like EPS that sit within either
Apple or Microsoft operating system and
and it's really about describing the
circle system in that way is there you
can have all these different tools
frameworks but a sexual system that it
sits in and where you use it and there
comes down to your values you know and
in what we're driving with counsel in
terms of the decision making is that
when we've gone through the climate
change risk frameworks that have been
developed they all human centered
and what we're saying there's actually
what is the risk to nature what is the
risk to the lien not just the rest to
people and and and and they're at the
heart of it what is the capacity and the
ability of the lane to care for nature
in people what is the capacity and
ability of nature to care for linden you
know that so when you start to think
about the types of decision-making we
need to be thinking about is putting all
those things in balance and and and more
recently what we've sort of seen in a
treaty settlement type process between
and some of your indigenous tribes in
the government is the creation of legal
christine elytis for a river hmm and and
for where my mother comes from a a sort
of mountainous region and and when the
government and their tribe were
negotiating what the settlement will
look like the government offered some
joint management of a national pact and
our tribes who actually that's not a
national pact to us that's how ancestor
and we don't want to jointly manage a
and sister so so the in negotiations got
suspended for almost two years because
of this impasse or will view in some
creative person been turned around well
why don't we create legal personality
and what we'll do is we'll share care of
this ancestor and and so so so in a
sense the rights of nature have been
acknowledged hmm and so when we think
about equity and equality it's not just
from a human sense it's also they you
know so unless at the heart of the
reciprocity between humanity and nature
in the way that we care for each other
and and and I find it fascinating to see
how
how much agility you have in like the
way that that you've worked with the
square system even the word like
observing the the wonderful work about
the Oakland Oakland Bay climate response
plan like I know from us talking before
that then we both agree that climate
change is just as you were saying
covered nineteen is a message that we
need to change our ways otherwise the
message is what will get harder you said
earlier before we started recording and
climate change is we are on the path to
the message is getting extremely hard
but we've both met at this meeting of
exploring regenerative development
within the Commonwealth and and and
talked a lot about working with Ben and
and Bill and Regenesis group and the one
of the things that they always invite
people to start from is not to start
from these problems of oK we've got a
community breakdown we've got youth
unemployment we've got climate change
and now we have economic issues and and
to actually start from reframing and
start start from potential and in a way
that you've framed the sort of over
Lansing that the two worldviews coming
together and forming some some kind of
basica Pisces in the middle where we can
learn something new together that is
speaking to potential or saying well
what would happen if we learned to
reconnect to that ancient lineage of
knowledge that is that understands that
the land is our ancestors that we we
come from this earth and then very
carefully not as a sort of rejection of
all technology but as a real
soul-searching inquiry into how do we
use this technology wisely so it doesn't
become our master rather than it stays
in service to to us and through that in
service to the land and to life M the
how do you find I mean this is a
beautiful example you just gave in terms
of how in that process of saying no we
don't want management of a national park
because we don't manage a land ancestor
to get to inviting the square system to
arrive at a point where they can
understand that - then do Aikido with
their system or create legal personage
for the land and it's a wonderful shift
in terms of how that land is related to
but it's that the powerful shift is that
you've actually changed the minds of the
square system of many people in the
square system we have to engage with
that way of thinking and but it feels
that these sort of things need to happen
really place sourced and place-based
yeah I think - because I think I think
what's really critical and what is that
we do have a Western system could
regenerative development thinking in a
circular system and and I think things
like climate change in in covered 19 is
driving us to at least become aware of
sequel systems thinking and I think that
what what has been working well within
Auckland is there and this is the impact
of the work they're building being have
been doing rien region Assessors there
we've got quite a significant number of
regenerative practitioners and thinkers
and and albeit at the moment as it's
being tied to placemaking which is
ironic to him in itself because place
sort of shapes you not the other area
but but you know it's a North American
urban sort of development - and and so
that worked at a program that I talked
about probably a 50 year program is this
opportunity and so what we're doing is
we're partnering with - Sukie
systems approaches the regenerative
thinking and indigenous thinking and and
and I think that's the key is that if we
can start to recirculate squeezed
systems as the square P agree on hope
and climate change covert nineteen
economic recovery crates that window for
us to sort of reimagine reframe in resit
they think because of we can get to
succour systems you know in Maori
culture when we greet each other we rub
noses in Heba homey
so what we're wondering that there's
they have those two circles have a Hong
E and and then by literally
recalibrating with the binoculars you
actually start to develop the shared
view in this new space where new
knowledge and this is where the
indigenous Asian of knowledge and
systems work ooh
because I think because of past because
of history the trauma we all carry we
need to find our way of at least coming
together and to do a hungee so that we
start to share their distance and and
and then it's recognizing their food
space so in our thinking we sort of have
this formula of one plus one equals
three and then and then together the two
binocular views actually creates that
infinity and so a lot of your framing
reason eights that type of cycle
thinking of sharing knowledge sharing
you know and and I think that and I
think that that like what you're saying
is that it's not about telling people
how to think it's inviting them to look
down the lens say hey look at that space
over there because often what happens is
the two systems are so caught up and
challenging each other the best way to
reconsolidate is find the third space
that we need to work together towards
and almost helping turn our way from
each other to their other opportunity
and that is about potential and I think
that for us everything are we anchor is
on well-being and there
systems thinking that well-being as a
given if your fuckup up our system is
whole you're anchored in place with
nature in his people their triangulation
because if you can get their anchoring
or that our Erie inhibiting the
replanting and net since then because
what we're doing is calibrating those
fuckup up our relationships calibrating
the value the reciprocal values that go
with it because they're almost like a
set of reciprocal obligations
responsibilities that we have with
nature nature his with us the state
symbiosis I would love to have you here
your reflection on something that they
want one framing of this relationship
that we all in and Bill sharp was a
friend of mine from the international
futures forum my book the three horizons
model he wrote a book on that and he
expresses it in a lovely way of saying
that all life is in tension between
being for oneself and being as part of a
larger whole and and it's and it's the
same like like it's not either I'm self
or I'm equal like either I'm ego or I'm
equal its I am and equal at the same
time and as Western people are starting
to wake up of the shortcomings of the
square system and one of their thinking
traps like you've heard us talk about a
lot about the big paradigm shift and but
it's a it's a pendulum swing it's a it's
again it's a square system way of
framing it off we're moving from this
thinking that is no longer serving us to
this new thinking that is so much better
because all the old is now not worth it
anymore the last time we did that swing
we forgot all the indigenous knowledge
and called it primitive and and and so I
I would love to hear from from the
wisdom that your lineage carries and
this ego eco relation
that people so often talk about like em
if we actually embrace ego in a
different way like that what I've
learned from working with the way of
counsel which comes out of the North
American native indigenous tradition is
you always ask three question
does it serve myself does it serve my
people and does it serve the whole or
life yeah yeah em how do we get into a
healthy relationship with providing for
our families and our personal immediate
needs but in the spirit that that is the
base work that we need to do of the
donut of the ground of yeah mother earth
that that that we that then enables us
to to be resourced to be in service of
the relationship between father's
grandmother the larger system how do you
relate to that from from your
perspective yeah I mean I you that
really resonates with me and you sort of
picked it up in the video
Yoel video in that last but weird talks
about you know quo call queer katawa
which is you me and us together that
same thinking and and I think that it's
almost like um that visualization of
ripples in the pool we're all of the
same pool and and as it representing
there the greater sense of me is in
though we yeah so so that's it seems of
self you know and and that is in that
sense of um power of a wider family my
community but also that is nature place
in people not just my human community in
that sense you know and in the minute
that isn't just an intellectual or how
nice were all one they're all part of
nature's like the way that sometimes
said in in in Western institutions
and like onion is with the ecology spoke
of the ecological self and they it's a
real embodied fully understanding
oneself adds life that with that comes
the the different perspective of time as
you were saying earlier the fifty year
project that you won't see finished and
the minute you you understand or one
understands like oneself as life there's
actually a connection to a certain
immortality purpose you know and and
that's why I think one thing we it sort
of standard controversial one of them I
think was a committee meeting what
counsel was I said you know what you
don't understand is that you're all
fighting for your survival as humanity
the thing though is that I'm really
confident that my fucking Papa is gonna
last forever because my DNA is made up
of sadness you know so so I will still
be around or my DNA was still in some
form
I don't have any control over that form
that's why our insistence to determine
the net since you know so because when
you sort of think about our fucker Papa
humility that the form we are now is and
what the form we started with and and
every hundreds of thousands of years you
know so so when we sort of think about
in and that's why what I love is that
there's a our essence and the cellular
level in a cellular level it's the same
DNA it's the same fuckup upper and the
fucker Papa that we share with nature
and other you know and so and there is
that um sort of I guess goes back to um
seeing the space that connects us you
know our ancestors were able to navigate
across the Pacific I
thousands of years because beer view was
the water connected or the island they
went aiming for this island it was
actually the water that connected
everything so so it's that sort of view
of connectedness in understanding so so
when we sort of see their whole living
system of the universe so we look to the
black of the space not all or sprinkly
of the stars you know that it's just
again those slightly different world
views of what I would say a circular
will view systems you as we actually
recognize the importance of space so so
even to the point that our ancestors had
names for the space in between atoms or
with an atom an ability describe what
that was you know early maps there our
ancestors drew in 1800 was almost this
bird's eye GPS view of the form of the
lane and when the cartography or that
time was though almost picture type to
one dimension all sort of view wasn't
the bird's eye view was the way that
right you know so so again that's their
whole ability of where you can locate
yourself to appreciate that view of
perspective and that's why I always come
back to the UM the view of running and
Papa the sky father earth mother on the
moon because we knew seed and it's one
of the images I'd like using in my
presentations is be able to and then I
guess that's one of those opportunities
is there it's enabling people do have a
view from the moon to really appreciate
the whole in the relationship of Adomian
Papa because when we earth beyond we
only see this up and down D yeah and
where's when you step to the side and
you see the full appreciation of that
relationship and so I think I think
and obviously it's how we because we've
almost got to do it as three generations
we sort of represent that middle
generation in terms of when thinking
about our parents we know with an
elderly memory and then you think about
our children in there our grandchildren
so so within three living generations we
influence another two or three beyond it
or they've been you know so so so we
need to move through this journey in
that way where we do not have an
intergenerational weight within our
families and because that's where the
transfer of values occur from generation
to generation and then they are being in
our modelling we're teaching our
children to be good grandparents in that
way you know but they've got to do it
with the near context within the tools
they hear with a near life but it
ultimately is about the transfer of
those values in the value of boats fucka
Papa relationships which i think is the
key to rien digitizing humanity and
whatever language you use it at a
fundamental base level we're really
talking about those intergenerational
symbiotic relationships just made me
tuned into something that I think
particularly like you earlier when you
spoke about if you think of it in the
Pacific since your ancestry goes back
fifty thousand years and it's all
Pacific Islanders and it's it's a
particular type like if you you could
almost say that the there's that the
ocean lineage and the land lineage of of
our ancestry that and and you're
representing the the ocean lineage and
and this image that you did that you
like just recently a friend of mine who
who last winter sale - Antarctica's
shared a map of
[Music]
the world that is ocean centric yeah so
yeah it's basically the land is just a
little bit in between and yeah and I'm
increasingly like like last week I was
invited to put some input into a
workshop that the Ocean Race which is
the former Whitbread around the world
and the Volvo Ocean Race not just the
Ocean Race and they've put this idea of
supporting ocean health at the center of
their communication strategy in using
the race around the world and all the
media attention to to really highlight
the issue of ocean health after the last
race around the world they did a lot of
research on ocean plastics and really
helped to highlight that issue and they
began to realize that that's a sort of
problem scent centred approach and and
actually using the concept of health is
much more circular already and in the
context I learned about a man that I've
you know Glenn Edney if you heard of
it's an organization in New Zealand
called ocean spirit all right
yeah and he wrote I wrote a book about
an exec can remember so the ocean is
alive or something and and as you were
just speaking I thinking to some extent
if we want to refit our human family
into the wider family and paying
attention to the fact that
life is animated water and that we all
from the oceans that our tears our ocean
that Alice blood is ocean salinity and
also understanding like in the in the
more problem conversation focused
conversations around climate change I
think we need to urgently and put the
ocean at the center because that's been
the big buffer but it's also the
long-term like if we don't
protect the oceans and of course we can
only do that if we change how how we
deal with the land as well
we're we're not going to avoid kind of
cataclysmic climate change how do you
how do you bring in to the climate
change conversation Orkut logic there
the Auckland climate change adaptation
plan this whole shift in perspective
towards um how critical the ocean is to
life yes so we've sort of I guess
anchored on water you know in the same
sort of seats and because in terms of
our part of our creation narratives what
we call y hora which is the life-giving
waters and and but also our spiritual
essence we refer to as way two to three
waters flow within you and so just their
whole reflection of the importance of
water the water cycle the fuck off of
water in that way and and and so one of
those so so the big sort of El El
pathway sort of transformational pathway
we've got what we call two too short to
medium type ships and three big shifts
that I framed this five key drivers a
few life in terms of certainly our body
response to climate change but also
advocating to council and so so these
that the two short to medium chefs is
really about a recalibration of business
as usual to reap to realign to do that
well-being sort of focus the second but
which often isn't being talked about and
you talk about that just their paradigm
shift from here to there
no one talks about the in could be
incremental shop so so we've talked
about how do we prepare communities for
the shift and and so there's a key piece
of work around educating informing
developing the tools to enable the show
so if we're gonna talk about a shift and
land use how you gonna talk to our
farmers on what that is about you know
in imposing new legislation around
emissions you know it's either blunt
stick or you know a carrot type where is
actually shifting the agriculture sort
of system to behave what we call like a
coy turkey a guardian custodian of those
reciprocal fucking Papa relationships
not just about land is a resource but
land is a ancestor in some of our
economic thinkers here are saying that
if if the businesses in their adopted
ethic of Kodiak eaten and treated
shifting away from natural resource is
you know something to manage to have us
to actually what we call a tongue is a
treasure your relationship totally
shifts with with the key of looking
after there is a place to resource the
minute so these are species of work
around preparing for the change and the
three big shifts one is what we're
calling the regeneration of ecological
systems and and let's look at a whole
catchment approach but with a specific
focus on parts of the catchment so we
talk about basically the ocean the
harbor wetlands and in their upper
catchment they're the work you need to
do is a whole system catchment so so you
know and and so but what we're looking
at is the cycle of water in those fucker
Papa relationships from the ocean and
then in the importance of wetlands
within that context because they're now
narratives the wetlands were actually a
domain there because some of our
ancestors like kangaroo who's the old
covenant - like Poseidon or niching so
in our in our pantheon of ancestors they
they sort of lived in a darkness of the
appearance of briefs and the
some breaks back CA da hey why don't we
sort of separate them so there's more
room for us and then some of the
siblings took sides with the parents
some didn't want them to be separated
some I'm gonna go up dead I was gonna go
mum and it created another ruction
across the siblings and and so we have a
narrative - why climate change exists in
their context and and basically Tong
Aurora who's their Neptune Cafferty
who's L in sister wounds Thani who
actually separated the two parents he's
sort of one of our ancestors for
humility for the forest birds all that
type of thing but it but he's also the
provider of human knowledge and so so
basically those siblings had this battle
because of the issues they had with each
other in the separation of the
appearance and what happened was -
ganged up on one who which was tougher T
and tougher he limped off the
battlefield and saying well okay
you won this time but I'm gonna take my
wrath out on your children so so the
name did teruki or tougher T Maori name
for the climate plain is refused to the
struggles or frustrations of tougher and
but also tongue or or the ocean as
biting at the heels of Tammy in the way
of erosion and all those sort of things
so big storm events so what we sort of
seen as witnessing the sparrow occurring
between our ancestors but what's
happened is part of the reason why
they're peddling is we've caused this
generations issues and so until we start
to reconcile with our ancestors and and
sort of make peace that we're going to
be caught in between this battle between
it's fascinating because ultimately what
you hinging the the whole frame on in
terms of him
a circular system restoration of the
water cycle and that is so much more
upstream response to climate change
basically it is the diluting of the land
and so many areas around the world
ultimately climate change is an upset
what does I got and yeah and so the
water and oceans really critical in and
so so when we am starting looking for my
Western science you and locate the
reduction of sedimentation or the
reduction in emissions and sort of
carbon targets reduction and carbon what
we see in the circular view is if they
become important because what they to
get to that level what we're creating is
breathing space for the ancestors is
that regenerating because we've seen it
in covert 19 so those targets and a
circle context they're important because
through our human is that what we're
trying to do is shift our behavior sort
of shift the Olympics and to a point
where those fucker proper systems can
regenerate themselves because they don't
need humans to did it what we've got to
do is manage shell behavior in a way to
help minimize that impact so that um
those systems can actually regenerate
themselves because they're the ultimate
fucker popper not as you know so and who
are we as humans do you say are we gonna
fix up nature we can reciprocate we can
and play our role but but ultimately in
this one the biggest thing through
covert 19 is city is watching globally
the regeneration of those systems
because of the fact that humanity got
locked up a bit and put away for a while
you know lynn ostrom
could you you said this earlier and now
you said it again
of course we need much more humility of
who are we in this largest cycle and and
like changed the narrative away from
what we're trying to save the earth or
like we're really trying to save our
future to some extent dire or acababa is
going to continue in in her cycles and
I'm reminded of as you know like when I
started writing my book there's one of
the key questions that that I came back
to was it was a question that mentor of
mine David Orr had asked me 10 years
before I started writing the book which
was when I asked him about really the
spiritual dimension of the shift that we
now had to do as as a species and he
said before we can answer the what we
need to do and how we might be able to
do it in order to create a sustainable
or regenerative human presence on earth
and we need to unser a deeper question a
much more difficult question and we need
to ask why are we worth sustaining what
is it in us that is worth worth it
that we are continuing as part of vaca
papa and for me I would love to hear
because on the one hand I completely
agree we need much more humility and not
take ourselves so important but there
must be some wisdom in in your lineage
that that also speaks to what is our
role like well what why are we here
because otherwise maybe maybe we should
just bow out as quickly as possible and
let the rest get on with I think I think
yeah I I think and this would probably
resonate with our Amazonian indigenous
communities - and and in
1 why are these sort of two words one
because we're just part of that system
or fuckup and and nfe if you think
Humanity is an awesome example of multi
copy the opportunity mother earth has
done because the diversity of humanity
in the different locations across the
planet and the way those places are
shaped us both in terms of and they so I
sort of go back to this tomb around
ecological cultural perspectives because
that's what the fuck up up is it's it's
the ecological cultural element and so
so that's one thing why because the
Earth Mother in sky father have deemed
it so that we're here long you know the
the other thing I think in Tunis from an
indigenous perspective because of their
close association in knowledge and
wisdom over generations of those systems
is that we are just the human
manifestation or the human voice of this
particular ecological system that my
ancestors are incurred and the same way
that our Amazonian relations are our
voice and so I made a comment when I
spoke at that in London was that if the
Amazon are the lungs of the earth then
indigenous people are re our spiritual
consciousness and and I think they're
there the opportunity in the re and
digitizing and recirculating of humanity
is the return to they in the Western
world there are a lot of people who
speak about our role as human beings is
to some extent the universe becoming
conscious of itself it's the it's the
ability of that hole to actually take
enough of a perspective that then
through this false separation that
dynamic of being for self and being part
of all actually creates a perspective
that will always be limited but in our
storytelling we can
together as human beings and and create
this multiple kaleidoscopic experience
of rule from within and that that is
ultimately the purpose of us that back
but then I think understanding all of
life as conscious and and even beyond
that possibly the rocks and the rivers
and and great well trees alike it is
that everything has a perspective on on
the whole as being in that dynamic yeah
being for oneself and being part of the
larger whole and we I guess we we do
bring in and that's where the time inter
is interesting we bring in that
awareness of patterns that we then turn
into our ancestry storytelling innocence
and therefore we create to some extent
through the this observation of the
system we are we also create the
capacity for some form of foresight we
might not know what's coming at us but
but to be wisely prepared to be able to
respond to future transformations comes
with that awareness and and and so maybe
this is where we were waking up to that
role with now that the dangers of
climate change in endangering our own
species and so many other species with
it is to say we need to
returned to trusting the feedback that
Gaia is giving also through us yeah I
totally agree with it and and if
anything through that observation it's
the because the so cause impotence you
know really important and and they're
just so in terms of some of our
knowledge is that we've been able to UM
constantly observe those patterns and
cycles over many generations so that so
a tion and and it's a and I guess it'll
be observation in in what you see feel
in here you know and so these are deeper
sense of that feeling and what you're
observing observing spirit and movement
all those sort of thing and and I think
that one of those things that we on
observation is the ability then to
actually hear the different voices of
nature so so we have we use the Tim
material which is language but we have
our human language the trees have their
language so the ability to TuneIn like
to what the perspectives of nature say
from beer view from their point of view
and I think that's the key is there the
ability to locate ourselves and those
different and appreciate those different
views so the view from the mountain the
view from the river the view from the
ocean and and and so there's all living
beings in in living elements they all
have their own consciousness in mixing
and and so and you sort of see that in
nature you sort of see it in the way
water responds to contamination and
other things you know so so and that's
where it comes back to that focus on
well-being but the well-being of those
connections that well-being all those
systems and and and then it becomes that
that greater self for me within the week
and they you know we are you know so
and that you know and and I and my
upbringing I'm a very I'm very much a
why in hell person you know because
listening to your elders when something
came into the meeting or whatever that
asked those sort of two questions why
and then the how and the how really is
so the wire is what is this what does
this opportunity how does a relate to us
else just them our way of thinking our
way of seeing our way of knowing and in
the how is how we're going to respond to
this opportunity challenge or whatever
it is within the context of practicing
our values and so so often people
getting caught up on the what and then
the who you know and we actually like
what you see it actually the we need to
answer or at least ask the wife is it's
not even about the answers just by
asking the question per se so those two
Christians elders used to ask I've had
on to say every situation even you know
do my masters and I'm now preparing for
PhD those are sort of almost the two
fundamental questions of or why and how
you know and so because if you can get
those two elements right then it doesn't
matter the what know what does the
mirror because whatever you'll be doing
is all going to be aligned to the why
and a half and in the what is very often
like again coming back to that
conversation at with Joel glance Berg he
often speaks of the the systems and the
structures in the probe that that we
actually see our monetary system our
governance system the houses we built
that the roads we put in and while there
the tracks the the process is really
behind it and when changed something
over time to just work with the tracks
design another building and change
layout of the city is it's just working
on changing the tracks again rather than
yeah I'm conscious that we've talked for
90 minutes
but it's been really wonderful I'm gonna
stop the recording now to give us a
brief moment to catch up on some of the
other thank you so much although this